I'm late. Darn it.
‪迟到了 该死
Your Royal Highness.
‪邸下
Where has your mind wandered off to?
‪您在想什么想得那么出神？
You couldn't hear me despite my attempts to grab your attention.
‪小的问了您好几次 您都没听见
I'll be late.
‪要迟到了
If we're done, I should go.
‪都穿戴完毕的话就走吧
Did you enjoy your drinks last night?
‪您昨日的酒席还愉快吗？
How could you have let him accompany you instead of me?
‪您怎么能舍下我而改带他出席呢？
I must say I felt left out.
‪小的真的很难过 邸下
There's no need to feel that way. I'll include you next time.
‪有什么好难过的？ ‪我下次一定会带你去
Thank you.
‪谢谢您 邸下
Is something wrong?
‪您怎么了？
No.
‪没事
Five steps, remember?
‪维持五步的距离
EPISODE 9
‪第 9 集
Why did I do such a thing?
‪我怎么会做出那种事？
I blame the alcohol.
‪真不该喝酒的
Why did I have to drink so much?
‪都怪我贪杯
Why aren't you heading inside?
‪你怎么还不进去？
Oh, well…
‪那个…
I was enjoying the fine weather
‪天气真晴朗
and the beautiful flowers.
‪花也很美 所以我…
Your Royal Highness, Royal Tutor Jung is here!
‪邸下 郑司书到了
NONEO
‪（《论语注疏》）
Last night--
‪昨日…
I deserve to die, Your Royal Highness.
‪臣罪该万死 邸下
Alcohol got the best of me
‪昨日是臣过于贪杯
which led to an unforgivable act on my part.
‪才会以下犯上对您做出古怪的举动
I seek your forgiveness.
‪请您饶恕 邸下
Of course. I understand.
‪我可以理解
Pardon?
‪什么？
That's how it is with alcohol, don't you agree?
‪酒就是会造成这种后果 不是吗？
Everyone makes a drunken mistake at least once in their lives.
‪每个人在酒席上都有可能会失误犯错
So don't be too concerned about it.
‪你不用太介意
We can just laugh it off.
‪那种事可以一笑置之
Of course.
‪果然…
You sure are a generous man who understands the effects of alcohol.
‪邸下不愧是精通酒道的大丈夫
I'm not one to make such mistakes,
‪臣本来不会犯下那种过错的
so I don't know what came over me.
‪不晓得昨日为何突然那么反常
You seemed so stunning under the moonlight and I…
‪因为您在月光下的模样太动人了 ‪臣才会情不自禁…
Oh, no… My goodness.
‪唉唷
That isn't what I meant.
‪臣不是那个意思
By the way,
‪那个…
I have something for you, Royal Tutor Jung.
‪我有东西要给你
They are candies.
‪那是正果
I hope it's the right amount of sweetness for you.
‪不晓得甜品是否合你的胃口
Why would you give me this?
‪您为何给我这个？
You went through a great deal regarding the envoys.
‪你因为使臣团之事劳心劳力
I seem to only be receiving your help, which is why I prepared a gift.
‪我时常承蒙你的相助 ‪所以才准备了这个
I hope that it suits your palate.
‪不晓得你会不会喜欢
I see you're back, Royal Tutor Jung.
‪你回来了啊 司书大人
Did you receive yours?
‪你收到了吗？
Receive what?
‪你是指什么？
Oh, good. You received one as well.
‪-他收到了 ‪-原来你也收到了啊
This is what His Royal Highness said as he handed it to me.
‪邸下在递给我时还说了这番话
"You went through a great deal regarding the envoys.
‪“你因为使臣团之事劳心劳力
How benevolent is that?
‪他就是如此仁慈
His eyes were warm when he told me
‪他说着“不晓得你会不会喜欢”时
that he hoped I would enjoy the candies.
‪展现的温暖眼神
He was also concerned that they may be too sweet for me.
‪加上他还担心甜品是否会合我胃口
So considerate.
‪那体贴入微的一面
It's the first in 20 years.
‪这是20年来头一遭
It's the first time in 20 years that my hard work was acknowledged.
‪我花了20年终于得到邸下的认可
I can finally understand
‪小的稍微能明白
why you broke out into a speech to give him high praise.
‪大人高声颂扬邸下的原因了
The sweetness is perfect.
‪不会太甜 味道刚好
Mine's bitter. Could it be bellflower?
‪我的有点苦耶 是桔梗口味吗？
I dismissed everyone at home, so do not be concerned.
‪我已支开所有家眷 你不必担心
I'm curious as to what brings you by, Your Majesty.
‪您特地前来是所为何事呢？殿下
Great Lord Changcheon.
‪国舅
Yes, Your Majesty.
‪是
Using the Ming envoy as leverage,
‪尚宪君上次利用明国使臣
Lord Sangheon obtained the development rights in Yeoyeon.
‪获得了闾延的开发权
What purpose do you think it will serve?
‪你认为他的目的为何？
I don't quite follow.
‪那是什么意思？
Yeoyeon is constantly invaded by barbarians.
‪闾延是蛮族出没的地带
Under the pretense of tightening security at the northern border,
‪他很快就会以守卫国境为由
he will try and grow his army.
‪培养自己的军队
-Then… -Build a private army of your own.
‪-那么… ‪-你也培养私兵
One that can stand against his.
‪足以与尚宪君抗衡的军队
You…
‪寡人
have my support.
‪会支援你
Your Majesty!
‪殿下
Yeong-ji, eat up.
‪英持 快吃
Why have you been so out of it?
‪你为何从刚才开始就失魂落魄的？
Aren't you going to have any? We'll finish them then.
‪你真的不吃吗？那我们全吃掉了哦
Sure. Help yourselves.
‪嗯 你们吃吧
Don't be like that and eat with us.
‪你别这样 一起来吃嘛
They are from His Royal Highness. We feel bad eating them alone.
‪听说这是世子邸下下赐的
She's right. Have some.
‪对啊 尝尝看嘛
Guys.
‪那个…
Forget it.
‪没事
What on earth is this about?
‪到底是什么事？
Don't just keep it to yourself and tell us already!
‪既然都出声了 就痛快地说出来 ‪不要吊我们胃口
Well…
‪那个…
So it's like this.
‪就是啊
Someone I know got drunk
‪我的一个熟人
and kissed the cheek of the person next to him.
‪喝醉后亲了身边的人的脸颊
The one that was kissed didn't seem fazed by it at all.
‪被亲的人一副若无其事的样子
Because that person nonchalantly brushed it off.
‪而莫名感到失落
Also, it turned out he wasn't the only one
‪此外 他本来以为对方只对自己好
that the person showed kindness and generosity toward.
‪结果那个人对其他人也是一视同仁
That upset him too.
‪所以他觉得很失落
Why do you think that is?
‪你们认为这是出于什么原因？
Seriously?
‪什么啊？
Hold on. Who are you talking about?
‪你现在是在说谁的事？
You or someone you know?
‪是你的亲身经历还是你的熟人？
Someone I know, of course.
‪就说是我的一个熟人了
Does he…
‪他
like that person?
‪喜欢那个人吗？
-What? -Isn't that what provokes jealousy?
‪-嗯？ ‪-喜欢一个人就会有那种反应啊
You want that person to only have eyes for you
‪希望那个人眼中只有自己
and you get upset when they aren't aware of your feelings.
‪对方若不懂你的心情就会忿忿不平
With expectation comes disappointment.
‪因为有了期待才会老是感到失落啊
No way.
‪拜托
I doubt it.
‪怎么可能啊？
From what I hear,
‪听说昨夜
His Majesty left the palace last night
‪殿下出宫
and wasn't back even at the end of curfew.
‪过了宵禁时间也没回来
Eunuch Cho, as his most trusted servant,
‪尚膳 你就仿如殿下的左右手
you would know why.
‪应该很了解个中缘由吧
I have no clue as to what you're saying.
‪这是什么意思？
His Majesty retired to his chambers early
‪殿下昨夜很早就入睡
and didn't step foot outside last night.
‪尔后从未踏出大殿一步
Again, you choose to play dumb?
‪你这次也不晓得？
Why do you keep doing this to me?
‪你为何要一直逼问我？
Don't you know I'm one of His Majesty's most loyal servants?
‪我是隶属大殿 专职服侍殿下的人
Ten years ago,
‪十年前
you came to me in tears
‪你哭着求我
begging me to save your dying wife.
‪救你生命垂危的妻子一事
Have you already forgotten that?
‪你似乎已经忘了啊
I believe I already paid back my debt in full.
‪我自认当时已彻底还清这个人情了
Yes, quite handsomely might I add.
‪是啊 你还得已经够多了
If you hadn't
‪若当时没有你
hidden the letter at the royal preceptor's house back then,
‪将信藏在翊善家中
I wouldn't have been able to eliminate those loyal to His Majesty.
‪我就无法将殿下的左右手全数歼灭
If he ever finds out about it,
‪若是殿下得知此事
I'm sure he'll be most touched by the loyalty you displayed.
‪他想必会十分赞叹你的忠心
Why not just tell me to pay with my life?
‪你倒不如取走我这条贱命
That I could do hundreds and thousands of times over.
‪那无论千百次我都甘愿奉上
Your life?
‪你那条命
You should hold onto that for the sake of His Majesty.
‪即便是为了殿下也要好好保全啊
Royal Tutor Jung.
‪你
What's wrong? Are you not feeling well?
‪你身体不舒服吗？
No.
‪不
No, it's nothing.
‪没有 我没事
I hardly think that's the case. You're flushed.
‪看起来不像没事 你的脸色很差
Just tell me. How do you feel?
‪跟我说说你哪里不适
Describe your symptoms.
‪哪里不舒服？
Well, you see…
‪就是啊…
It feels like…
‪我一直觉得
something is squeezing my chest.
‪这里闷得发慌
Multiple times a day, my heart pounds erratically.
‪终日有好几次心脏都狂跳个不停
And I'm spacing out all day and I can't think straight.
‪而且还感到思绪恍惚 ‪完全打不起精神
Wait. They sound like the symptoms I came across in a book.
‪等等 那些症状我曾经在书上看过
Is that so? Then do tell us what he's suffering from.
‪那是什么症状？说来听听
Your face flushes involuntarily
‪脸会下意识变得通红
and your mood goes from excited
‪心情会突然大起大落 时而雀跃
to suddenly depressed.
‪时而悲伤
Sometimes, you see and hear things,
‪有时候会出现幻觉和幻听
while a certain someone keeps appearing in your dreams.
‪可能在梦中 ‪也会时常出现某个特定人物
Exactly!
‪你说得没错
-Yes, I knew it. -What does he have?
‪-果然就是那个 ‪-那是什么？
You're lovesick!
‪那是相思病啊！
Pardon?
‪什么？
Who is the young lady that is driving you crazy?
‪是哪个女子让你如此神魂颠倒？
What?
‪那个…
There's no young lady.
‪什么女子？
That's not the case.
‪没那回事
Come on. There's no need to be embarrassed.
‪唉唷 这有什么好害羞的？
-Just give us a name-- -Hold on!
‪-稍微跟我们透露一下… ‪-那个…
I forgot that I needed something from the library.
‪我忘了有事要到书库一趟
-I had better get going. -Royal Tutor…
‪-我先走了 ‪-郑司…
-Royal Tutor Jung. -Royal Tutor Jung!
‪-郑司书！
Royal Tutor Jung!
‪郑司书！
I'm definitely right.
‪绝对错不了
Who could it be?
‪是谁啊？
Any ideas?
‪会是谁呢？
Hey.
‪郑司书
You look awful. Is something wrong?
‪你的脸色怎么这么差？ ‪发生什么事了吗？
It's nothing.
‪没有
Nothing's going on. Absolutely nothing.
‪没什么啦 一点事都没有
As if. Unbelievable.
‪什么没有？真是的
Take a look over there.
‪你看那边
They're the dancers for the upcoming banquet
‪她们是本次宴会的舞姬
and they've had all the men within the palace gawking at them.
‪她们简直让宫中男人 ‪血脉偾张、鼻血直流
No!
‪不是的！
That can't be.
‪不是的
That's not possible. It just isn't.
‪不可能会有那种事 不是的
What do you mean?
‪你是指什么？
What is he on about?
‪什么东西不是？
No way.
‪好
Find inner peace. Let's read some books.
‪回归平静 来读一下书吧
Why do I keep seeing…
‪为何一直看到…
What on earth?
‪怎么回事？
Why do you keep appearing?
‪你为何一直出现？
Leave.
‪走开
Go away!
‪你给我走开
Have you lost your mind?
‪你吃错药了吗？
Is it really you, Your Royal Highness?
‪您真的是邸下吗？
What brings you here?
‪您怎么会来这里？
I'm looking for a book, of course.
‪我当然是来找书的
I see.
‪这样啊
That reminds me.
‪对了
Did you enjoy
‪之前给你的正果
the candies I gave you?
‪还合你胃口吗？
Yes, of course.
‪是
They were delicious.
‪那很美味
I'm glad.
‪真是太好了
I…
‪那个…
Forgive me, Your Royal Highness.
‪臣惶恐 邸下
I'm not feeling well and must excuse myself.
‪我今天身体不太舒服 先失陪了
Go ahead.
‪你先走吧
What's with Royal Tutor Jung?
‪他怎么了？
Where could my daughter be going
‪你打扮得这么漂亮
after dolling herself up this beautifully?
‪是要去哪里啊？我的掌上明珠
-Do I look pretty? -I couldn't recognize you at first.
‪-我漂亮吗？爹 ‪-我没认出你是我女儿
I thought an angel had come to our house.
‪还以为是天上下凡的仙女呢
Unbelievable. Dad, please.
‪什么啊？爹真是的
Now that you mention it, I do see a resemblance.
‪听你这么一说 确实是有点像呢
My lady,
‪小姐
Lady So-eun is here.
‪素恩小姐来了
Already?
‪这么快啊？
Not so fast.
‪慢一点
So-eun!
‪素恩！
Goodness, are you all right?
‪你没事吧？
Not a second goes by without me worrying about you.
‪我因为你时时刻刻都提心吊胆的
You got here early.
‪你来得真早
-Are you ready to go? -Yes.
‪-都准备好了吗？ ‪-嗯
Where exactly are you going that has her this excited?
‪你们到底是要去哪 ‪让她这么兴高采烈？
I'm headed to the palace to run an errand for my father
‪我要进宫替我爹跑腿
-and Ha-gyeong wanted to join me. -The palace?
‪-贺庆说要与我同行 ‪-进宫？
I'll get going, Dad.
‪我出门了 爹
Don't wander off to places
‪不要随便乱晃
and follow So-eun around. Do you hear me?
‪一定要跟在素恩身边 听到了没？
Gosh, this is amazing.
‪天啊 真壮观
I wonder what it'd be like to live here.
‪生活在这种地方会是什么感觉啊？
Can you wait for me here?
‪你可以在这里等我一下吗？
I'll take this to my father and come right back out.
‪我把这拿给我爹后马上就回来
Sure. Don't worry about me and go.
‪好 你就去吧 不用担心
Who are those two young ladies?
‪那些孩子是谁？
They don't seem familiar.
‪之前好像没有见过
while the other is the daughter of the Minister of War.
‪和兵曹判书卢学修大监之女
You seem to be from a noble family.
‪你似乎出身于两班世家
Why are you here in the palace alone?
‪为何独自在宫中游走？
There is nothing to see here,
‪这里什么都没有
so head another way.
‪你去别的地方吧
Your Royal Highness.
‪邸下
The Queen Dowager requests your presence.
‪大妃殿在找您
-The Queen Dowager? -Yes, Your Royal Highness.
‪-大妃殿？ ‪-是的
Your Royal Highness?
‪邸下？
He's the Crown Prince?
‪他是邸下？
No way.
‪真不敢置信
The selection of a princess?
‪拣择？
I thought we were done speaking of this.
‪那件事之前就有了定论
I still stand with what I said last time.
‪儿臣的意思就如同上次所说的那般
The Crown Prince is still unwell, so we'll revisit the idea some other time.
‪世子身体尚有微恙 ‪此事就再往后推迟吧
Until when will you let others question the weight of his crown?
‪你究竟何时才要稳固他国本的地位？
We must hold a royal marriage, so he can produce an heir.
‪得尽快举行国婚 才能孕育后代
This can't be postponed any longer.
‪不能再延宕下去了 主上
Commander Yoon accompanied him on a trip to see his father-in-law.
‪殿下偕同内禁卫长去拜访了府院君
That is all I know.
‪其他的我也一无所知
Crown Prince, what is your take on this?
‪世子的意思呢？
Is marriage what you desire?
‪你想举行嘉礼吗？
The envoy reception only just ended.
‪使臣团不久前才来访
Another big event such as a royal wedding
‪倘若又举行国婚这种大型盛事
will burden our people.
‪恐怕会对百姓造成过大的负担
Please be more considerate of them
‪恳请王祖母顾及百姓的感受
and postpone the royal wedding just a little bit.
‪将国婚日程稍微往后推迟
Regarding the selection of a princess,
‪关于世子嫔的拣择事宜
I hope that you will be patient until I readdress this matter.
‪在儿臣另外跟您禀奏之前 ‪请先耐心等候
Is it because…
‪您真的…
you are set on passing the crown to Prince Jehyeon?
‪打算将邸下之位传给齐贤大君吗？
If that is not the case,
‪若非如此
why are you in constant opposition to His Royal Highness' marriage?
‪为何每次都要出面 ‪阻挠邸下举行国婚？
Lord Sangheon, I suggest you watch your words.
‪尚宪君 请注意你的言词
You were already married and were a father to His Royal Highness
‪殿下在邸下这个年纪时早已举行国婚
when you were his age.
‪并生下了邸下
If it's the people Your Majesty wishes to do right by,
‪若您真的为百姓着想
then a royal marriage and the birth of an heir must be a priority.
‪就得尽早让世子迎娶世子嫔 ‪延续王室命脉
The people and members of the royal court
‪百姓及朝廷众臣
eagerly await His Royal Highness' wedding.
‪全都翘首盼望着邸下的嘉礼
That is enough.
‪别说了
The selection of a princess
‪反正世子嫔的拣择
has always been conducted by the ladies of the royal palace.
‪是属于内命妇所掌管
I will take matters into my own hands.
‪这件事本宫自会处理
JAGYEONGJEON
‪（慈庆殿）
I wish to return to my quarters.
‪回大殿吧
Is something wrong, Your Majesty?
‪您怎么了？
It's nothing.
‪没事
What should we do, Your Royal Highness?
‪这该如何是好啊？邸下
The Queen Dowager is clearly adamant on the matter
‪大妃娘娘的口吻如此强硬
which means it'll no longer be possible to postpone your marriage.
‪现在似乎无法再推迟了
Fret not, Your Royal Highness.
‪不要紧的 邸下
You've been preparing for what you know is inevitable.
‪您早就料到会有这一天 ‪所以提前做了练习啊
You know what to do.
‪您也很清楚该怎么做
You will take the hand of your betrothed like so.
‪您就这样牵住
Then say, "My heart now belongs to you."
‪再说“我倾心于你”…
I'd rather be alone.
‪我想独处一下
Please leave.
‪你们都出去吧
Yes, Your Royal Highness.
‪是
This would definitely work.
‪这招马上就能奏效
The Crown Prince?
‪邸下吗？
That's what I said.
‪我就说啦
You should have seen the way
‪你不晓得他护住我的姿态
he took me by the waist to stop me from falling.
‪有多么帅气
Could this be what is known as destiny?
‪这就是所谓的命中注定吗？
I have a new goal.
‪我有了一个目标
I'm going to be the Crown Princess.
‪我非成为世子嫔不可
For sure.
‪一定要
Jan-i, over here.
‪嗯 潺怡
I'll get going then.
‪我先走了
Don't be distracted on your way home
‪你不要分神游荡到其他地方
and please get home safely, Crown Princess-to-be.
‪路上请小心 世子嫔娘娘
Crown Princess-to-be? Stop that.
‪世子嫔娘娘？唉唷
I'll get going then.
‪我走了
Lady So-eun!
‪小姐！
-Stop. -Catch me!
‪-站住 ‪-来抓我啊
-Give it back. -It's mine!
‪那是我的 还给我
That's mine!
‪那是我的
My gosh!
‪天啊！
Goodness. Oh, no…
‪这该怎么办？
What…
‪真是的
Forgive me, my lord. Are you all right?
‪小的惶恐 大人 您没事吧？
Are you kidding me?
‪这是怎样啊？
I'm truly sorry. Please let me wipe it clean.
‪小的惶恐 我立刻替您擦干净
Stop that, you dirty wench.
‪真是的 真够脏的
How dare you lay your hands on me.
‪喂 你竟敢用你的脏手碰我
-My goodness! -Oh, dear!
‪-天啊！
Jan-i, are you all right?
‪潺怡 你没事吧？
My lady.
‪小姐
What do you think you're doing?
‪你这是成何体统？
What do I think I'm doing?
‪什么？你问我成何体统？
Really?
‪成何体统？
Talk about having a lousy day.
‪我今天真够倒霉的
I'm glad.
‪真是太好了
Let me apologize for the trouble my maid caused.
‪很抱歉 是我的婢女不小心弄脏了你
I hope my apology can appease your anger.
‪我代替她向你谢罪 请你消气
Compensation will be made for your ruined clothes.
‪你受损的衣物 我会全额补偿
Unbelievable. Do I look like I need monetary compensation?
‪该死 是把我当成乞丐吗？
Let's see.
‪这样啊？
How exactly will you pay me back?
‪那你打算怎么赔偿我？
With that sweet little face of yours?
‪要用你这张标致的脸蛋来偿还吗？
Please stop this!
‪你岂敢如此无礼？
Do you have any idea who you're talking to, you crazy wench?
‪该死 你知道我是谁吗？
And who might you be?
‪你是谁啊？
Lord Jung?
‪公子
What…
‪这是…
Let go of my hand. Drop it.
‪还不放手？放开我
We have spectators, Lord Changun.
‪周遭耳目众多 君大监大人
Please be careful.
‪请自重
Do you have no idea who you're speaking to?
‪你这臭小子竟敢对我说这种话？
Wait.
‪等等
Oh, I see.
‪我知道了
You're the Crown Prince's royal tutor, aren't you?
‪你就是世子的老师嘛
Did being in his good graces lead you to believe
‪怎么？你以为跟世子走在一块
that you had some sort of authority?
‪自己也成了什么大人物吗？
Who are you to order me to be careful?
‪竟敢目中无人地要我自重？
You must have a death wish today.
‪你今天是真的不想活了吧？
Let me make it come true.
‪那我当然要如你所愿
Hasn't your house arrest only been lifted recently?
‪您不是不久前才刚服完安置刑吗？
Causing a commotion will only put you in a bad position.
‪您这样引起骚动 ‪最终麻烦的会是您自己
What? You brazen rat.
‪天啊 看看你这臭小子
I guess it's admirable.
‪天啊 真帅气
I dare you to push your luck again.
‪你再嚣张啊
Do it.
‪再嚣张看看啊
That's enough.
‪到此为止吧
You are out of line.
‪真是放肆
How dare you stand in the way of the royal family.
‪竟敢出手阻挡王室宗亲
This is quite the party we're having, don't you think?
‪今天真是个大日子啊
Unbelievable.
‪唉唷 真是的
Uncle, you should also show dignity as a member of the royal family.
‪也请叔父展现出 ‪贵为王室宗亲应有的风范
I'm glad you mentioned that.
‪你提到这点正好
It is why I mean to teach these lowlifes
‪我正想让这些低贱的家伙
the custom and order of our class system.
‪好好见识一下何谓阶级制度
So stay out of my way today.
‪所以你今天就别阻拦我
Come here.
‪过来
Didn't I specifically tell you that you have done enough?
‪我方才分明说了到此为止
Damn it!
‪天杀的！
What are you looking at, you bastards?
‪有什么好看的？你们这群混账！
You may take her home.
‪快送她回去吧
My nephew, you have made a huge mistake today.
‪侄子 今天你可是犯了一个大错
Rather than teaching those lowlifes a lesson,
‪你非但没有好好教训他们的无礼
you stood in my way when eyes were on us.
‪甚至还在众目睽睽下阻拦我
It was you who almost made a mistake.
‪差点犯下过错的人是叔父才对
She is the daughter of the Minister of Personnel.
‪她是吏判大监之女
It won't be wise to create problems.
‪恣意冒犯并非明智之举
What?
‪什么？
Darn it.
‪可恶
Why are they all chummy anyway?
‪他们为何都厮混在一块？
Has marriage been suggested between them?
‪难道是缔结婚约了吗？
It could've been dangerous for you. Why did you intervene?
‪你差点就身陷险境了 ‪为何要出面阻拦呢？
It being a dangerous situation is exactly why I took action.
‪因为差点身陷险境 ‪所以在下才要出面啊
I see a different side to you every time we meet, Lord Jung.
‪我每次见到公子 ‪你都展现出不同的面貌
And I'm curious to see what more you have to offer.
‪也让我期待日后将会见到你何种面貌
Expressing my gratitude with words is not enough.
‪口头道谢已无法表达我的感激之情
Jan-i is like a sister to me, you see.
‪我对潺怡就像亲妹妹般爱护
It must have startled you, so please get some rest.
‪你今天应该受到很大的惊吓 ‪快回去休息吧
Jan-i, don't feel too bad about it and get some rest.
‪你也不要放在心上 回去歇着吧
I hear you had an audience with the Queen Dowager today.
‪听说你白天曾到大妃殿一趟
Being a Crown Prince
‪世子之位
can feel futile at times.
‪还真是无常
One must accept a loveless marriage
‪只因为国家大事这个理由
just because it's a state affair.
‪就得缔结毫无情意的婚姻
Maybe…
‪如何？
you could perhaps put in a word for me?
‪王兄能替我说情一下吗？
Petition that the wedding be postponed for your dear younger cousin's sake.
‪出面替我这个弟弟请求延后嘉礼吧
I wouldn't mind taking advantage of your influence for once.
‪借此机会我也想沾沾王兄的光
Your Royal Highness…
‪邸下
I was just joking.
‪我只是说笑的
There's no need to take it so seriously.
‪你不必那么严肃地看待那些玩笑话
It's impossible to joke around with you.
‪看来以后都不能跟你开玩笑了
May I…
‪我能问你
ask you something?
‪一个问题吗？
Have you ever loved someone, Your Royal Highness?
‪你没有心上人吗？邸下
Pardon?
‪什么？
Here you are teasing a groom-to-be.
‪你这么说是在戏弄准新郎
It's why I'm asking.
‪因此我才要问你
Have you ever harbored romantic feelings for anyone?
‪你此生是否曾有过意中人？
You've never mentioned it before.
‪因为你从未提起过啊
Of course, I had someone.
‪我怎么会没有呢？
It was back when I was young.
‪那发生在我很小的时候
A scuffle one day at the palace
‪我曾跟一个进宫的孩子起了争执
led to us falling into a pond.
‪而一同失足落水
Only I knew how to swim,
‪那孩子不会泅水
so I saved the child.
‪是我救了他一命
"Yeon-seon"?
‪“莲膳”？
Dam-i is a pretty name,
‪虽然垣这个名字也很美
but I wanted to call you by a more meaningful name.
‪但我总想用更特别的名字来叫你
Although it was a brief encounter,
‪虽然我们认识的时间很短暂
it still is a memory…
‪但那段时光
I haven't been able to forget.
‪却仍是我难以忘怀的回忆
I guess…
‪或许
you could say it was my first love.
‪那就是我的初恋吧
Royal Tutor Jung?
‪郑司书
What brings you by the palace this early in the morning?
‪你怎么这么早就进宫了？
I have a favor to ask, Your Royal Highness.
‪臣有个请求 邸下
Please…
‪请给我…
give me a hug.
‪一个拥抱
What are you saying?
‪什么意思？
Royal Tutor Jung, are you ill?
‪郑司书 你哪里不舒服吗？
Yes, I'm unwell.
‪对 我不太舒服
I'm a mess, you see.
‪我很难受
So please…
‪所以恳请您
Indulge me this once.
‪给我一个拥抱就好
You're obviously not thinking clearly. How could you ask that of him?
‪你的状况好像很严重
Let me embrace you instead.
‪我来给你一个拥抱
I hope you find your strength,
‪请振作起来
Royal Tutor Jung.
‪郑司书
Are you better now?
‪这样可以了吗？
Let's head out.
‪我们走吧
Why on earth did you do that, Your Royal Highness?
‪您到底为何要那么做？
How could you have given in to that ridiculous request?
‪您怎么能接受他那荒谬的请求？
The people passing by saw you two.
‪路过的宫人全都看到了
He said he's a mess and that he's under a lot of stress.
‪他说他不舒服 又很难受
Exactly! How could one ask a favor for such reasons
‪所以说啊 不管是因为不舒服 ‪而提出那种请求的人
and how could one indulge him?
‪或是应允那个请求的人
Why you two acted that way is beyond me!
‪小的完全猜不透 ‪你们两位到底在想什么
Because I like him, that's why.
‪因为我喜欢他才那么做的 出于喜欢
Liking him is one thing but…
‪不是啊 喜欢是一回事…
My goodness.
‪唉唷
Pardon?
‪什么？
I'll soon be married…
‪我很快就要举行婚礼了
so I should be allowed to at least do that.
‪作为最后一次 ‪让我那么做也不为过啊
Right?
‪是吧？
Your Royal Highness!
‪邸下
Don't you worry…
‪你别担心
for I'll soon get rid of these feelings.
‪我很快就会断了这份情意
Did you hear about the upcoming princess selection?
‪你有听说即将举行 ‪世子嫔拣择的消息吗？
A princess selection, my goodness.
‪天啊 拣择
Is our Crown Prince finally entering adulthood?
‪我们邸下终于要成为 ‪真正的大人了吗？
You'll soon be busy once the princess selection begins.
‪一旦开始进行世子嫔拣择 ‪各位又要忙起来了呢
-Of course. -What did you just say?
‪-对啊 ‪-那是什么意思？
A princess selection?
‪拣择？
The Crown Prince is getting married?
‪邸下要成亲了吗？
Why are you surprised by this?
‪你为何那么吃惊？
His Royal Highness is at an age where he should get married.
‪邸下也是男人 到了适婚年龄 ‪当然就得成家啊
Yes, of course.
‪-那当然 ‪-是啊
This will excite maidens across the country.
‪看来又要搅乱一池春水了
His Royal Highness may be aloof, but he is quite handsome.
‪世子邸下虽然性情冷淡 ‪但外型却很俊俏
You're darn right he's handsome. Just like me.
‪他当然很俊俏 就跟我一样
Royal Scholar Yang, you have the face of a jester.
‪辅德大人 你是戏子的面相
A gallant, you say?
‪吃软饭的
Are you still feeling unwell?
‪你的身体很不舒服吗？
If that's the case, the lecture--
‪很难受的话 今日的书筵…
I hear a wedding is imminent.
‪臣耳闻您即将举行嘉礼
That's right.
‪没错
It should have happened a while ago
‪老早就该举行了
but it took longer than expected.
‪日子却拖得比预期还要晚
Congratulations, Your Royal Highness.
‪恭喜您 邸下
It's great news.
‪真是个令人欣喜的消息
I appreciate it, Royal Tutor Jung.
‪谢谢你 郑司书
Please let me know
‪若有什么我能效力的地方
if I can help in any way.
‪随时都可以告诉我
I doubt you'll find anyone with more knowledge regarding women.
‪关于女人的事 很少人像我这么精通
I'll consider it.
‪那当然
Once the process begins,
‪当嘉礼开始进行
I will look forward to your help.
‪就要请你多多帮忙了
That's right.
‪是啊
It's not like anything could have happened anyway.
‪反正这件事打从一开始就没有希望
What could come out
‪他是男人
of having feelings for a man…
‪又贵为世子
who is the Crown Prince with a wedding underway?
‪喜欢上一个 ‪马上就要成亲的人有什么用？
Get a grip on yourself, Ji-un.
‪清醒一点 郑至韵 你清醒一点
Get a grip.
‪清醒一点
What's with the serious look on your face?
‪你怎么独自面色凝重地坐在这里？
You're here.
‪你来啦
How are the preparations for the wedding coming along?
‪嘉礼准备得怎么样了？
That one-sided love you once mentioned.
‪你之前提过的那个单相思对象
Why did you never confess your feelings?
‪你为何不跟对方表白？
Because I thought the feelings would never be reciprocated.
‪因为我认为这份感情得不到回应
I was also worried that telling her would only put a distance between us.
‪同时也担心那会成为她的负担 ‪而与她渐行渐远
You should have told her though.
‪但你还是该尝试一下的
Who knows how people will react?
‪人心是无法预测的
Maybe I should have.
‪我应该要试着表白吗？
Actually, no.
‪不
It's not common
‪我要跟对方心意相通
So I'd rather keep them to myself.
‪所以我打算独自珍藏这份感情
I will not burden her…
‪我不想给她负担
or have any regrets.
‪也不想徒增任何遗憾
That's how it'll be.
‪就是这样
How corny, Lord Jaeun.
‪真是肉麻啊 君大监
What? That's what you say when I opened up to you?
‪什么？我好不容易向你吐露我的烦恼
How dare you.
‪你竟敢对兄长…
You…
‪喂 你…
You did that on purpose knowing I'm afraid of water.
‪你明知道我很怕水还这么卑鄙
Okay, fine. We'll stop this.
‪好 我不闹你了
Gosh.
‪真是的
Didn't you say
‪你是不是说过
you fell into a pond at the palace when you were young?
‪小时候进宫时曾经失足溺水？
I told you multiple times already.
‪我说过无数次了
On the day of the banquet when I first met Dam-i.
‪功臣宴时初次遇到垣的那天
She saved my life.
‪是她救了我一命的
A scuffle one day at the palace
‪我曾跟一个进宫的孩子起了争执
led to us falling into a pond.
‪而一同失足落水
Only I knew how to swim,
‪那孩子不会泅水
so I saved the child.
‪是我救了他一命
When did you say the girl disappeared?
‪你说她大概是什么时候消失的？
Why do you suddenly ask?
‪为何突然问这个？
She was an orphan taken in by monks who came to stay at the palace.
‪她无父无母 自幼在寺里长大 ‪之后才进宫的对吧？
-I should get going. -What?
‪-我得先走一步了 ‪-喂
Hyun!
‪显
Where did they go?
‪到哪去了？
Oh, right.
‪对了
NOKUNGAK
‪（绿云阁）
LONGING, WAIT
‪（恋 期）
It wasn't…
‪原来…
a dream.
‪那不是梦
That was…
‪那个…
The alcohol got the best of me and I…
‪我突然感到酒气冲上脑门才会…
Forgive me, Your Royal Highness.
‪臣惶恐 邸下
Please forgive me.
‪臣惶恐
It's all right.
‪别说了
It seems as though I've become quite approachable to you.
‪看来郑司书自认跟我变得十分亲近
Well, that's not what it is.
‪不是那样的
Those.
‪那个啊
-Sorry? -Could I take a look at them?
‪-什么？ ‪-可以让我摸摸看吗？
She told me to give these to you if I ever met you.
‪她说若是遇到你 就将这个转交给你
She told me
‪她说这能在你难受的时候
they would help you stay strong when things get hard…
‪成为你的依靠
just like…
‪因为这对她来说
they had been helpful for her.
‪曾经也是她的依靠
For a long time, I wondered…
‪我长久以来都很想知道
of the man you came to be.
‪你会变成什么模样
LONGING, WAIT
‪（恋 期）
I thought it was a dream.
‪我还以为那是个梦
I believed that my impure feelings for you
‪我以为那是我对您抱持的不纯之情
came to haunt me.
‪反映在梦境中
However…
‪然而…
it wasn't…
‪那个…
STAY, LONGING
‪（停 恋）
…a dream.
‪却不是梦
I will believe you
‪若您说那是当下被动摇了
if you say the feelings were momentary.
‪我会相信您的
But it wasn't for me.
‪我并非如此
It wasn't admiration from a subject.
‪我不是以臣子之心相待
I thought it was my loyalty to you.
‪我曾以为自己是出于忠心
But it was affection.
‪结果却是恋慕之情
I have a deep affection for you, Your Royal Highness.
‪我爱慕着您 邸下
Although you're a man and the Crown Prince of this nation,
‪即便您是男儿身 ‪又贵为这个国家的王储
I…
‪我还是…
love you.
‪爱慕着您
What do you mean His Royal Highness isn't at the palace?
‪邸下不在宫中？
He must know that
‪她不可能忘了
the Queen Dowager is expecting to see him this afternoon.
‪下午要到大妃殿一趟啊
So His Majesty finally gave his blessing for the royal marriage?
‪殿下终于同意着手进行拣择了？
You are So-eun, the daughter of the Minister of Personnel?
‪你是吏判之女素恩吗？
I will endure it.
‪我会承受的
Whatever people say, I will endure it all.
‪无论世人如何对我指指点点 ‪我都会一肩扛下来
Perhaps, it might have been better if we had never met again.
‪倒不如打从一开始 ‪就不要重逢还比较好
Are you ordering me to leave?
‪您是在命令我离开吗？
Subtitle translation by: Hye-lim Park
‪字幕翻译：钟见悦